Hester Lynch Piozzi Letters to Dr. William Makepeace Thackeray
Yale Center for British Art, Rare Books and Manuscripts
Hester Lynch Piozzi Letters to Dr. William Makepeace Thackeray
1795-1816
MSS.29
Yale Center for British Art, Rare Books and Manuscripts
0.2
1 volume
The collection comprises 98 autograph letters from Hester Lynch Piozzi to her friend and physician, Dr. William Makepeace Thackeray, dated between April 16, 1795, and September 10, 1816, compiled and bound together in a single album.
Piozzi, Hester Lynch, 1741-1821
Thackeray, William Makepeace, 1770-1849
Arrangement
The letters are bound in chronological order, with undated material bound at the end.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Paul Mellon Collection.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The collection comprises 98 autograph letters from Hester Lynch Piozzi to her friend and physician, Dr. William Makepeace Thackeray, dated between April 16, 1795, and September 10, 1816, compiled and bound together in a single album.
The letters cover Mrs. Piozzi's life with her second husband, the musician Gabriel Piozzi, his illness and eventual death in March 1809 from gout, and the subsequent years of widowhood. The letters are chiefly written from Brynbella, Mrs. Piozzi's villa in the Vale of Clwyd. The correspondence includes news of family matters and a detailed record of her husband's lengthy illness, the latter often accompanied by requests for medical advice or professional visits from Thackeray.
The letters are frequently interspersed with literary and other allusions and anecdotes, political gossip, and bon mots. They include references to many friends and associates of Mrs. Piozzi, including Dr. Johnson ("Dear Dr. Johnson was not difficult to be imposed on where the heart came in question, but he would not have believed this story about Shakespeare"), David Garrick ("Is not it curious to reflect that the year MY old friend burst upon mankind in the same way, - was marked by contagion: & people called it the Garrick Fever") and Mrs. Siddons, as well as comments on the Napoleonic Wars ("All is gathering fast to a head; Buonaparte has pledged himself to effect our ruin, & they spare us 200,000 men").
Two of the letters consist of original verse: item 82, a poem of 24 lines entitled "A song made in time of the mutiny by desire of some loyalists who dined at the Crown & Anchor Tavern Tune Nancy Dawson"; and item 80, a poem of 7 lines, untitled.
Most of the letters are signed either in full or with the initials HLP, but a few are either unsigned or bear the signature "Brynbella," the name of Mrs. Piozzi's villa. Also included in the collection is a letter announcing the death of Mr. Piozzi, written on behalf of Mrs. Piozzi by her friend Mrs. Moore.
The letters in the present volume are not included in The Piozzi letters: correspondence of Hester Lynch Piozzi, 1784-1821 (formerly Mrs. Thrale), edited by Edward A. Bloom and Lillian D. Bloom (1989-1993).
Biographical / Historical
Hester Lynch Piozzi (née Salusbury; other married name Thrale), 1741-1821, was a prominent diarist, author, and patron of the arts in late 18th century Britain. She is also known as a notable friend of Dr. Samuel Johnson. After Johnson's death, she published Anecdotes of the late Samuel Johnson, LL.D., during the last Twenty Years of his Life (1786) and Letters to and from the late Samuel Johnson, LL.D (1788). Other notable works by Piozzi include: Observations and reflections made in the course of a journey through France, Italy, and Germany (1789); British synonymy, or, An attempt at regulating the choice of words in familiar conversation (1794); and Retrospection, or, A review of the most striking and important events, characters, situations, and their consequences, which the last eighteen hundred years have presented to the view of mankind (1801).
Dr. William Makepeace Thackeray (1770-1849) was a notable physician at Chester (in the county of Cheshire) and uncle of the famous novelist of the same name.
Bibliography
Piozzi, Hester Lynch. The Thrales of Streatham Park [edited] by Mary Hyde. Cambridge: Harvard University Press, [1977].
Piozzi, Hester Lynch. The Piozzi letters: correspondence of Hester Lynch Piozzi, 1784-1821 (formerly Mrs. Thrale), edited by Edward A. Bloom and Lillian D. Bloom. Newark: University of Delaware Press, c1989-1993.
Authors, English -- 18th century -- Correspondence; First Coalition, War of the, 1792-1797; Gout; Medicine -- Great Britain; Napoleonic Wars, 1800-1815; Physicians -- Great Britain; Great Britain -- Politics and government -- 1789-1820; Letters; Abercorn, James Hamilton, Duke of, 1811-1885; Broster, John, -1816; Chappelow, William; Dore, Maria; Garrick, David, 1717-1779; Hoare, Henry Merrick, 1770-1856; Hoare, Sophia Thrale, 1771-1824; Hodgkins, Samuel; Johnson, Samuel, 1709-1784; Keith, Hester Maria Elphinstone, Viscountess, 1764-1857; Leak, Alexander, 1776-1816; Moore, John, 1752-1820; Mostyn, Cecilia Margaretta Thrale, 1777-1857; Mostyn, John, 1775-1807; Napoleon, Emperor of the French, I, 1769-1821; Parry, Caleb Hillier, 1755-1822; Pepys, Lucas, Sir, 1742-1830; Piozzi, Gabriele Mario, 1740-1809; Piozzi, Hester Lynch, 1741-1821 ( Correspondence); Piozzi, John Salusbury; Siddons, Sarah, 1755-1831; Thackeray, Elizabeth, approximately 1780-; Thackeray, Martin, 1783-1864; Thackeray, Selina Martha, 1806-1835; Thackeray, William Makepeace, 1770-1849 -- Correspondence; Streatham Park (London, England)
- Letter to William Makepeace Thackeray, 1795 April 16; Piozzi, Hester Lynch, 1741-1821; 4 pages (2 leaves): autograph letter, signed; 23 x 19 cm. (Box [1])
  Scope and Contents
  Sent from Streatham Park. Piozzi discusses her return from a journey and the state of affairs at home. People mentioned: the princess and her husband, the king and queen, Mrs. Piozzi's daughters, Mr. Lloyd of Wygfair, Mrs. Siddons and her baby, Mr. Chappelow, one of Dr. Thackeray's brothers, Mr. Mostyn, Hamilton, Mrs. Heaton, Miss Ashbourne, Mr. Moore, and Mr. Piozzi.
  Correspondence; Piozzi, Hester Lynch, 1741-1821 -- Correspondence; Thackeray, William Makepeace, 1811-1863 -- Correspondence
- Letter to William Makepeace Thackeray, 1795 May 5; Piozzi, Hester Lynch, 1741-1821; 4 pages (2 leaves): autograph letter, signed; 23 x 19 cm. (Box [2])
  Discusses a trip to the opera and dinner at Llannerch, and current affairs, including the current war. People mentioned: Lady Abermarle, Eliza Martin, Mrs. Leo, Hillisberg, Duchess of Rutland, Captain Molloy, Mrs. Siddons, Mrs. Hamilton, Lady Louisa Gordon, the Duchess of Bedford, Mr. Sheridan, Thackeray's brother, Mrs. Heaton, Mr. Moore, Mrs. Crespigny (?), Mr. Mostyn, Cecilia, and Mr. Piozzi.
  First Coalition, War of the, 1792-1797; Correspondence; Opera -- England -- London; Piozzi, Hester Lynch, 1741-1821 -- Correspondence; Thackeray, William Makepeace, 1811-1863 -- Correspondence
- Letter to William Makepeace Thackeray, 1795 June 4; Piozzi, Hester Lynch, 1741-1821; 4 pages (2 leaves): autograph letter, signed; 23 x 19 cm. (Box [3])
  Discusses possible remedies for Mrs. Piozzi's ailment. People mentioned: Cecilia, Miss Heaton, Mrs. Heaton, W. Mead, Peane the Poulterer, Lady Owen, Mr. Chappelow, 'our' Bishop, Bennett Williams, Sir Edward Lloyd, a captain, Mrs. Leo, Sir Frederick Eden, Princess, Mr. Miles, Prince, Mr. and Mrs. Mostyn, Mrs. Myddelton, and Mr. and Mrs. Moore.
  Correspondence; Piozzi, Gabriele Mario, 1740-1809; Piozzi, Hester Lynch, 1741-1821 -- Correspondence; Thackeray, William Makepeace, 1811-1863 -- Correspondence
- Letter to William Makepeace Thackeray, 1795 June 12; Piozzi, Hester Lynch, 1741-1821; 4 pages (2 leaves): autograph letter, signed; 24 x 19 cm. (Box [4])
  Discusses her daughter's safe return, marriage and inheritance arrangements, and Dr. Thackeray's retirement. People mentioned: Mrs. Piozzi's daughter, Mr. Thrale, Mr. Thrale's daughter, Lord Chancellor, Mr. Mostyn, Cecilia, Mrs. Mostyn, Mr. Piozzi, Miss Heaton, the prince, the Stadtholder.
- Letter to William Makepeace Thackeray, 1795 June 22; Piozzi, Hester Lynch, 1741-1821; 4 pages (2 leaves): autograph letter, signed; 25 x 20 cm. (Box [5])
  Tells the story of a young noble lady who ran away from home to work at an ale house. People mentioned: the Prince of Wales, the Duke and Duchess of York.
- Letter to William Makepeace Thackeray, 1795 September 20; Piozzi, Hester Lynch, 1741-1821; 1 page (1 leaf): autograph letter, signed; 12 x 26 cm. (Box [6])
  Discusses Mr. Piozzi, gout, and Dr. Thackeray's recovery. Piozzi invites Dr. Thackeray to visit in October. People mentioned: Mr. and Mrs. Mostyn, Mrs. Piozzi's three daughters, and Mr. Piozzi.
- Letter to William Makepeace Thackeray, 1796 July 29; Piozzi, Hester Lynch, 1741-1821; 2 pages (1 leaf): autograph letter, signed; 23 x 19 cm. (Box [7])
  Discusses Sir Roger Mostyn's death and Mr. Piozzi's gout. Piozzi also discuss the situation in Europe, particularly mentioning Italy and Portugal. People mentioned: Sir Roger Mostyn, Mr. Piozzi, Mr. Moore, and the Queen of Portugal.
  Correspondence; Piozzi, Gabriele Mario, 1740-1809; Mostyn, Roger, 1734-1796; Piozzi, Hester Lynch, 1741-1821 -- Correspondence; Thackeray, William Makepeace, 1811-1863 -- Correspondence
- Letter to an unidentified recipient, 1796 November; Piozzi, Hester Lynch, 1741-1821; 1 page (1 leaf): autograph letter; 12 x 20 cm. (Box [8])
  Undated; "Nov. 1796" supplied in graphite at a later date. Dr. Thackeray is gravely ill. The letter ends hurriedly and may be unfinished. People mentioned: Dr. Thackeray and Mrs. Heaton.
- Letter to William Makepeace Thackeray, 1796 November; Piozzi, Hester Lynch, 1741-1821; 1 page (1 leaf): autograph letter; 11 x 20 cm. (Box [9])
  Undated; November 1796 surmised from continued discussion of Dr. Thackeray's (?) illness. Mr. and Mrs. Piozzi send their condolences and a book to a sick friend. People mentioned: Mr. Piozzi, Mrs. Piozzi, and a friend.
  Correspondence; Thackeray, William Makepeace, 1811-1863 -- Correspondence; Piozzi, Hester Lynch, 1741-1821 -- Correspondence
- Letter to William Makepeace Thackeray, 1796 November; Piozzi, Hester Lynch, 1741-1821; 2 pages (2 leaves): autograph letter, signed; 23 x 19 cm. (Box [10])
  Discusses hopes that Dr. Thackeray is better and urges him to read Johnson's Life of Mr. Richard Savage. People mentioned: Lady Macclesfield, Colonel Brett, Mr. Seward, Dr. Johnson, Shakespeare, Mrs. Heaton, and Mr. Piozzi.
  Correspondence; Thackeray, William Makepeace, 1811-1863 -- Correspondence; Piozzi, Hester Lynch, 1741-1821 -- Correspondence; Johnson, Samuel, 1709-1784
- Letter to William Makepeace Thackeray, 1796 November 24; Piozzi, Hester Lynch, 1741-1821; 1 page (1 leaf): autograph letter, signed; 24 x 19 cm. (Box [11])
  Wishes Dr. Thackeray a speedy recovery from his illness. People mentioned: Mr. Moore and Mr. Piozzi.
- Letter to William Makepeace Thackeray, 1796 December 23; Piozzi, Hester Lynch, 1741-1821; 1 page (1 leaf): autograph letter, signed; 23 x 19 cm. (Box [12])
  Discusses Dr. Thackeray's ill health and his good deeds. People mentioned: Jane Shore.
- Letter to William Makepeace Thackeray, 1797 January 24; Piozzi, Hester Lynch, 1741-1821; 1 page (1 leaf): autograph letter, signed; 25 x 19 cm. (Box [13])
  Piozzi worries about Cecilia Mostyn's illness and asks Dr. Thackeray to calm her fears. Piozzi wonders at the cause of the sickness and asks Dr. Thackeray how he managed to bleed Cecilia Mostyn. People mentioned: Cecilia Mostyn, Dr. Thackeray, and Mr. Moore.
  Correspondence; Thackeray, William Makepeace, 1811-1863 -- Correspondence; Piozzi, Hester Lynch, 1741-1821 -- Correspondence; Mostyn, Cecilia Margaretta Thrale, 1777-1857
- Letter to William Makepeace Thackeray, 1797 January 28; Piozzi, Hester Lynch, 1741-1821; 2 pages (1 leaf): autograph letter, signed; 25 x 19 cm. (Box [14])
  Discusses the improvement of Mrs. Mostyn's health and current fashions. Piozzi also discusses the war, mentioning French losses and the political situation of the British Isles. People mentioned: Mrs. Mostyn, Mr. Piozzi, Irishman, Frenchmen, the Opposition, and the Ministers.
  First Coalition, War of the, 1792-1797; Clothing and dress; Correspondence; Mostyn, Cecilia Margaretta Thrale, 1777-1857; Thackeray, William Makepeace, 1811-1863 -- Correspondence; Piozzi, Hester Lynch, 1741-1821 -- Correspondence
- Letter to William Makepeace Thackeray, 1798 February 24; Piozzi, Hester Lynch, 1741-1821; 4 pages (2 leaves): autograph letter, signed; 22 x 19 cm. (Box [15])
  Dr. Thackeray has been called out of retirement for his "Talents and Virtues." Piozzi discusses her health and the current war effort. People mentioned: Dr. Thackeray's mother, Mr. Piozzi, Sir Lucas Pepys, Dr. Haygarth, Buonaparte, Milton, Mr. and Mrs. Hamilton and their daughter, and Mr. Holman.
  First Coalition, War of the, 1792-1797; Correspondence; Piozzi, Hester Lynch, 1741-1821 -- Correspondence; Thackeray, William Makepeace, 1811-1863 -- Correspondence
- Letter to William Makepeace Thackeray, between 1798 and 1803?; Piozzi, Hester Lynch, 1741-1821; 2 pages (1 leaf): autograph letter, signed; 23 x 19 cm. (Box [15a])
  Piozzi discusses gout, influenza and illness and complains about the quality of inn pens and paper. People mentioned: Dr. Parry, Dr. Haygarth, Dr. Thackeray, and an unnamed lady friend.
- Letter to William Makepeace Thackeray, 1803; Piozzi, Hester Lynch, 1741-1821; 3 pages (2 leaves): autograph letter, signed; 26 x 20 cm. (Box [16])
  Piozzi discusses her husband's gout and rumors of sickness in Bristol, London, and Paris. People mentioned: Dr. Thackeray's brother, Mr. Piozzi, Dr. Parry, Louis Seize, the Members of Parliament, and an unnamed Friend.
- Letter to William Makepeace Thackeray, 1803?; Piozzi, Hester Lynch, 1741-1821; 2 pages (2 leaves): autograph letter, signed; 24 x 19 cm. (Box [16a])
  Piozzi discusses the worsening illness of her husband and the illness of others and her joy at finally returning home after an unpleasant journey. People mentioned: Mr. Piozzi, Dr. Thackeray, Mr. Moore, Rich and Maria.
  Correspondence; Piozzi, Gabriele Mario, 1740-1809; Thackeray, William Makepeace, 1811-1863 -- Correspondence; Piozzi, Hester Lynch, 1741-1821 -- Correspondence
- Letter to William Makepeace Thackeray, 1803; Piozzi, Hester Lynch, 1741-1821; 3 pages (2 leaves): autograph letter, signed; 26 x 20 cm. (Box [17])
  Piozzi asks Dr. Thackeray to send her some syrup of white poppies to ease Mr. Piozzi's gout, cough, and fever. People mentioned: Mr. Piozzi and Mr. Moore.
  Correspondence; Thackeray, William Makepeace, 1811-1863 -- Correspondence; Piozzi, Hester Lynch, 1741-1821 -- Correspondence; Piozzi, Gabriele Mario, 1740-1809
- Letter to William Makepeace Thackeray, 1803 December 13; Piozzi, Hester Lynch, 1741-1821; 3 pages (2 leaves): autograph letter, signed; 26 x 20 cm. (Box [18])
  Piozzi thanks Dr. Thackeray for his kindness and for sending poppy syrup, though the vial broke on its way to her home and Mr. Piozzi had to make do with a different and unpleasant sort of poppy syrup. Mr. Piozzi is ill, but not as severely as in the past, however, Mrs. Piozzi tells Dr. Thackeray to be prepared to visit if she suddenly calls. People mentioned: Mr. Piozzi and Mr. Moore.
- Letter to William Makepeace Thackeray, 1803 December 20; Piozzi, Hester Lynch, 1741-1821; 4 pages (2 leaves): autograph letter, signed; 26 x 20 cm. (Box [19])
  Discusses Mr. Piozzi's improving health and outlines plans for Mr. and Mrs. Piozzi to visit Dr. Thackeray on their way to London. Mrs. Piozzi mentions her husband's valet's survival of a burst blood vessel, and discusses the threat of Napoleon. People mentioned: Dr. Thackeray, Mr. Piozzi, friends of Dr. Thackeray, Hodgkins, Allen, Mr. Moore, Paul and L. Kirkwall.
- Letter to William Makepeace Thackeray, 1803 December 23; Piozzi, Hester Lynch, 1741-1821; 3 pages (2 leaves): autograph letter, signed; 26 x 20 cm. (Box [20])
  Piozzi discusses Mr. Piozzi's relapse into gout and asks Dr. Thackeray to come as soon as possible. People mentioned: Dr. Thackeray, Mr. Piozzi and Mr. Moore.
- Letter to William Makepeace Thackeray, 1803 December 25; Piozzi, Hester Lynch, 1741-1821; 2 pages (1 leaf): autograph letter, signed; 23 x 20 cm. (Box [21])
  Discusses Mr. Piozzi's continued illness and possible fever and hallucinations and the affairs of some acquaintances. People mentioned: Mr. Piozzi, Mr. Mostyn, Dr. Myddelton, Mr. Moore, Jones of Pontriffeth, Maid Allen, Selina, Lady Kirkwall and Dr. Currie.
  Correspondence; Thackeray, William Makepeace, 1811-1863 -- Correspondence; Piozzi, Gabriele Mario, 1740-1809; Piozzi, Hester Lynch, 1741-1821 -- Correspondence
- Letter to William Makepeace Thackeray, 1803 December 27; Piozzi, Hester Lynch, 1741-1821; 2 pages (2 leaves): autograph letter, signed; 24 x 20 cm. (Box [22])
  The blister gives Mr. Piozzi some relief and Mrs. Piozzi discusses other remedies. Hodgkin's also has a blister and is taking foxglove because his pulse is too quick. Piozzi asks Dr. Thackeray to provide advice for the treatment of both men. People mentioned: Mr. Piozzi and Hodgkins (the valet).
  Correspondence; Piozzi, Hester Lynch, 1741-1821 -- Correspondence; Thackeray, William Makepeace, 1811-1863 -- Correspondence; Piozzi, Gabriele Mario, 1740-1809
- Letter to William Makepeace Thackeray, 1804 January 8; Piozzi, Hester Lynch, 1741-1821; 3 pages (2 leaves): autograph letter, signed; 26 x 20 cm. (Box [23])
  Mr. Piozzi's health has improved, but Hodgkins still has a dangerously high pulse, despite the foxglove and the blood that was drawn. Piozzi wishes the French would attack now to let the English volunteers do their duty and to "keep them from wicked thoughts" while there is no harvest. She also describes a cartoon about Napoleon. People mentioned: Dr. Thackeray, Mr. Piozzi, Hodgkins (the valet), Buonaparte and John Bull.
  Correspondence; Napoleonic Wars, 1800-1815; Piozzi, Hester Lynch, 1741-1821 -- Correspondence; Thackeray, William Makepeace, 1811-1863 -- Correspondence; Piozzi, Gabriele Mario, 1740-1809
- Letter to William Makepeace Thackeray, 1804 June 14; Piozzi, Hester Lynch, 1741-1821; 3 pages (2 leaves): autograph letter, signed; 26 x 20 cm. (Box [24])
  Piozzi offers congratulations on Dr. Thackeray's marriage to a widow with children. People mentioned: Dr. Thackeray, Squire Jones, Mr. Piozzi, Mrs. Thackeray and Miss Holford.
  Correspondence; Thackeray, Elizabeth, approximately 1780-; Piozzi, Hester Lynch, 1741-1821 -- Correspondence; Thackeray, William Makepeace, 1811-1863 -- Correspondence
- Letter to William Makepeace Thackeray, 1804 December 17; Piozzi, Hester Lynch, 1741-1821; 4 pages (2 leaves): autograph letter, signed; 23 x 19 cm. (Box [25])
  Piozzi discusses the weather and the walnut trees at Brynbella. Mr. Piozzi's gout has returned and Mr. Moore makes him drink castor oil. She also discusses the popularity of Roscius, comparing it to The Garrick Fever. People mentioned: Mr. Piozzi, Mr. Moore, Mrs. Clough, Mrs. Thackeray, Mrs. Thackeray's children, Mrs. Mostyn and Roscius.
- Letter to William Makepeace Thackeray, 1805 August 5; Piozzi, Hester Lynch, 1741-1821; 3 pages (2 leaves): autograph letter, signed; 25 x 19 cm. (Box [26])
  Piozzi congratulates Dr. Thackeray on his wife's pregnancy. Mr. Piozzi's gout has returned, but Nelson won a great victory against the French. People mentioned: Mr. Piozzi, Sir Robert Calder, Admiral Nelson, General Elliot, Mrs. Thackeray and Miss Lydia.
- Letter to William Makepeace Thackeray, 1805 August 19; Piozzi, Hester Lynch, 1741-1821; 3 pages (2 leaves): autograph letter, signed; 25 x 20 cm. (Box [27])
  Piozzi asks for charity for the orphaned grandson of a sister of the Dean of Chester. Piozzi hears that her cousin Mary's son (and his wife) are dead, leaving their child in poverty to solicit aid from relations. Piozzi asks Dr. Thackeray to help find this young man employment. It is unclear if the grandson of the sister of the Dean of Chester and the grandson of Mrs. Piozzi's cousin Mary are the same person. People mentioned: Mr. Piozzi, the grandson of a sister of the Dean of Chester, Mrs. Piozzi's cousin Mary, Dr. Cotton and Dr. Thackeray.
- Letter to William Makepeace Thackeray, 1806 November?; Piozzi, Hester Lynch, 1741-1821; 1 page (1 leaf): autograph letter, signed; 23 x 19 cm. (Box [28])
  Mr. Piozzi's gout has worsened. Mrs. Piozzi requests Dr. Thackeray's immediate presence. People mentioned: Dr. Thackeray, Mr. Piozzi and Owen.
- Letter to William Makepeace Thackeray, 1806 November 15; Piozzi, Hester Lynch, 1741-1821; 2 pages (2 leaves): autograph letter, signed; 23 x 19 cm. (Box [29])
  Piozzi begs Dr. Thackeray to come as quickly as possible. Mr. Piozzi's gout remains severe. People mentioned: Mr. Piozzi.
- Letter to William Makepeace Thackeray, 1806 November 18; Piozzi, Hester Lynch, 1741-1821; 3 pages (2 leaves): autograph letter, signed; 25 x 20 cm. (Box [30])
  Piozzi begins the letter Tuesday night describing Mr. Piozzi's improved health, though she asks for Dr. Thackeray's advice because Mr. Piozzi still displays some worrying symptoms. She adds a postscript written at midnight saying that Mr. Piozzi's condition has worsened and fearing that he will not recover. People mentioned: Mr. Piozzi, Mrs. Jones, and Mrs. Thackeray.
- Letter to William Makepeace Thackeray, 1806 November 22; Piozzi, Hester Lynch, 1741-1821; 4 pages (2 leaves): autograph letter, signed; 23 x 19 cm. (Box [31])
  Discusses Mr. Piozzi's improved health; he has finally gotten out of bed with the help of food and five bottles of Madeira. Mrs. Piozzi laments that Europe will not so quickly recover from "her...illness." Piozzi describes dramatic weather and twice addresses Dr. Thackeray in French. People mentioned: Mr. Piozzi, Mrs. Thackeray, Rev. Mr. Taylor, Mr. Jones, Queen Elinor and fair Rosamund.
  Correspondence; Piozzi, Hester Lynch, 1741-1821 -- Correspondence; Piozzi, Gabriele Mario, 1740-1809; Thackeray, William Makepeace, 1811-1863 -- Correspondence
- Letter to William Makepeace Thackeray, 1806 December 5; Piozzi, Hester Lynch, 1741-1821; 3 pages (2 leaves): autograph letter, signed; 23 x 20 cm. (Box [32])
  Piozzi discusses Mr. Piozzi's improving health and his treatment--he prefers the "blisters" to the "bark." She congratulates Dr. Thackeray on the birth of his daughter Selina. People mentioned: Mr. Piozzi, Mr. Moore, Selina Thackeray and Mrs. Thackeray.
  Correspondence; Thackeray, Selina Martha, 1806-1835; Piozzi, Hester Lynch, 1741-1821 -- Correspondence; Piozzi, Gabriele Mario, 1740-1809; Thackeray, William Makepeace, 1811-1863 -- Correspondence
- Letter to William Makepeace Thackeray, 1806 December 10; Piozzi, Hester Lynch, 1741-1821; 3 pages (2 leaves): autograph letter, signed; 22 x 20 cm. (Box [33])
  Mr. Piozzi's health continues to mend. Mrs. Piozzi discusses the "new scheme of blockading Great Britain." People mentioned: Mr. Piozzi, Mr. Piozzi's "Attendant Men," Bowen, Mr. Mostyn, Mr. Mostyn's wife and children, and Selina (Dr. Thackeray's daughter).
  Napoleonic Wars, 1800-1815; Correspondence; Piozzi, Hester Lynch, 1741-1821 -- Correspondence; Piozzi, Gabriele Mario, 1740-1809; Thackeray, William Makepeace, 1811-1863 -- Correspondence
- Letter to William Makepeace Thackeray, 1807 February 17; Piozzi, Hester Lynch, 1741-1821; 4 pages (2 leaves): autograph letter, signed; 23 x 20 cm. (Box [34])